Uh, that's that's how it played out.
There was never any intent to take Bin
Laden alive. My name is John Kiryaku.
I'm a former CIA counterterrorism
officer and after the 9/11 attacks, I
became the CIA's chief of
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
where I led a series of raids that
resulted in the capture of dozens of
al-Qaeda fighters. I went on to be the
chief investigator at the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee. Today, we'll be
looking at counterterrorism scenes in
movies and TV and judging how real they
are.
Yeah, literally none of
that is true to life. But that's that's
what makes you love James Bond. First of
all, I'll say almost no officers carried
weapons. You have to be in a in a post
that is rated as high or critical threat
for uh terrorism. Uh, the only posts
where I ever carried a gun
were Athens and uh and Pakistan. Um,
otherwise I was I was always unarmed.
And you're not going to walk into
Parliament just opening fire. That's
just it's just not real life.
You got
me. Now here's your prize. Love it. that
as part of this film was absolutely
believable. In this James Bond movie,
Raul is considered to be what's called a
lonewolf terrorist. Somebody who's not a
member of an organized group. He acts
alone. Those are more prevalent than you
might think. And the person who comes to
mind most immediately is Carlos the
Jackal. This is a guy who successfully
kidnapped, get this, all at once, every
single oil minister in OPEC. But for all
intents and purposes, Carlos was a lone
wolf. Attacking public transport is
quite easy. Transportation is probably
the weak link in our infrastructure. In
Tokyo, there was an attack some years
ago uh by uh Amrikio, terrorist group.
It was more of a cult really that that
adopted terrorism as a as a uh policy uh
where they they spread poison gas
through the ventilation system and
killed a whole bunch of people. So
although we've not seen something like
this happen, uh it is possible that it
could. Well, may I give it a couple of
different ratings? So shooting up
parliament uh no sorry one but threat to
transportation while it's not you know
crazy action-packed like we saw with you
know uh Raul blows a hole in the the
ceiling that's not going to happen but
that threat is real. So I'd say seven or
eight good evening Mr. Hunt the weapons
you recovered in Bellarus were confirmed
to be VX nerve gas capable of
devastating a major city. So, at the
beginning of this clip, Ethan Hunt was
told that he's looking for nerve gas,
right? That's true. I mean, every major
intelligence service hunt for chemical,
biological, and nuclear weapons. $50
million to let Benji go. They come one
step closer. Shoot me.
Stop. Yeah. You know, there there are
elements of reality in that. Sometimes
part of the job, especially in
counterterrorism, is that you have to
put yourself in dangerous positions like
that. Well, there was there was one
situation where I was I was handling a
double agent. He didn't know that I knew
he was a double agent. And he didn't
know that I knew that he had been
instructed to shoot me in our final
meeting. So, we had prepared a team just
like you saw here in the clip to protect
me. It's not as sexy as this is with a
beautiful woman sitting there next to
you, you know, with a gun in your ribs
to do you the favor of killing you. Um,
you know, and the the technology isn't
on your contact lens. Uh, but the idea
is correct. on realism. I'd give it like
a four because the danger of that of
that final meeting, sure, is accurate.
It's a little cooler than it is in real
life and the rest of it's just
Hollywood. Attack at Camp Chapman was a
catastrophe for the CIA. I actually
worked with several of those people.
There was a source who had been offered
up to us by a a third country
intelligence service. he got right into
the center of the base. It was a failure
at every step of the way. There were
there were almost immediate improvements
uh after this happened. So, suicide
attacks happen. Um they're not supposed
to happen at that grand scale, but it's
always a
danger consistent with all
counterterrorism raids, especially
counterterrorism raids related to
al-Qaeda. First of all, they're all at
night, usually in the middle of the
night. Uh in Pakistan, we only did our
raids after 2 am or at or after 2 am
because you want people to be asleep.
You want them to be caught unawares.
That's what they did in this case. Now,
they came in to the bin Laden compound
with all accounts uh that's that's how
it played out. There was never any
intent to take Bin Laden alive. There
are
similarities in the real life raid that
the movie got wrong and they got it
wrong on purpose.
In the moon rate analysis, a targeting
analyst is going to pour through
sometimes millions of pieces of data.
Put this thing together where you can
say we've narrowed it down to this
neighborhood in Abadabad, Pakistan. The
one thing that bothers me the most is
when Hollywood perpetuates the myth that
torture prevented acts of terrorism or
disrupted acts of terrorism. And to me,
that myth is dangerous in that it
affects public opinion. This was a film
that the CIA made a policy decision on
that it was going to cooperate fully to
the point where senior CIA officers gave
them
inappropriately classified briefings
over a classified mockup of the Bin
Laden compound. Okay, that's that's
chargeable under the Espionage Act. The
CIA just turned it over. Why? Because it
made the CIA look good. This clip as a
clip, the clip that we just watched, I
would give it a nine because it is
pretty much the way things played out.
But no, it wasn't the torture that gave
up Osama bin Laden.
My name is Ali Sufan. I'm with the FBI.
There's only one interrogation technique
that works. Rapport building. Another
person that you saw in the clip was Ali
Sufan. Ali uh Ali and I worked together
both in Yemen and in uh in Pakistan. Ali
Sufan went to the secret site and Ali
did what the FBI has been doing. He
established a rapport with his prisoner
and after about six
weeks of this rapport development with
Ali, he finally opened up and he gave us
actionable information.
We stop the music when he starts
talking, then he can sleep. Learned
helplessness. So, briefly in this clip,
you see one of those contract
psychologists, um, James
Mitchell, explaining to Ali
Sufan what his goal is. His goal is
learned helplessness. That's the goal.
The goal is to completely break him
psychologically. Now they did that by
using what they called enhanced
interrogation techniques. Some of them
were very very minor and mild. It sort
of worsened to things
like sleep deprivation. We saw that in
the clip with the loud music and you saw
Abubeta hanging by his uh wrists uh with
handcuffs. So he can't kneel or sit or
lay or get comfortable in any way.
One, two, three.
Where is the next attack? Waterboarding,
which most Americans now know about, and
was supposed to be the worst. And it's
pretty darn bad. We waterboarded each
other in training just to see what it's
like. It's awful. Sleep deprivation and
the cold cell actually killed more
people where, you know, it's already
50°. You're you're so cold, you're
naked, and then you have this ice water
thrown on you, and your body just stops
working. you go into into uh into shock
and just die. You can put whatever
euphemism you want on it. You can call
it enhanced interrogation tech. I don't
care what you call it. What we did to
some of those people was just illegal.
Just to be transparent, I was the script
adviser on that film and um it was
written by a friend of
mine. Everything in that film was true.
Everything was based on the Senate
torture report. In this clip, we see
Adam Driver, who is portraying the
Senate Intelligence Committee's lead
investigator on the CIA's torture
program. What was released was not the
Senate torture report. It was a very
heavily redacted copy of the executive
summary of the torch report. The torch
report itself was 5,000 pages long. The
executive summary was 500. They
waterboarded him 183 times. Everything
they got from him was either a lie or
something they already had. Well, now
what we saw in this clip was Adam Driver
uh briefing Senator Diane Feinstein.
this who at the time was the senior
republic senior Democratic senator from
California and chairwoman of the Senate
intelligence committee on his findings
his findings were that Khalik Muhammad
who was the mastermind of the 911
attacks was
waterboarded
187 times Abeda was waterboarded 83
times neither one of them gave up any
actionable intelligence uh during
torture I objected to the CIA's use of
so-called enhanced interrogation
techniques which I believe to be
torture. And I went public with that
information in December of 2007. I
resigned from the CIA to go into the
private sector. All this time, by the
way, I'm waiting for somebody to come
out and say something. And nobody said
anything. As a result, I was prosecuted
and served 30 months in prison. But I'm
glad I did. Somebody had to do it. And
in the end, I think it made the country
a safer place. This clip and the movie,
the report as a whole is a 10. A strong
10. We got lucky jacking with NATO
satellite. And that's the location right
there. Yeah. Cinnamon.
Yeah. I can't tell you how many
times we droned weddings or funerals and
then we'd have to say, "Oh, sorry.
Here's a million dollars. Our
apologies."
So that is
unfortunately true. Uh what's not true,
it wouldn't be up to an individual case
officer to order an air strike. She
could call the head of CTC and recommend
the air strike and he says go for it.
Members of the Pakistani Taliban vowed
retaliation for the alleged attack. Ham
Hakani has been martyed. Yeah, this kind
of thing happens all the time. So in
this clip, this member of the Pakistani
Taliban named Hakani uh was was the
target. The Hakani network is a real
network, a real terrorist network uh
right on the Afghan Pakistani border.
They're really Afghans. But anyway, be
that as it may, we learn later on in
this season that Hakani was not at the
site and had lived. That is also
something that's quite common. You know,
rarely rarely does the American
government admit to a mistake. There was
a mistake in Afghanistan just days
before we we pulled out where we killed
this, you know, highv value target who
was loading missiles into the trunk of
his car. He was actually not only not a
high-value target, he was an employee of
the American government and we just blew
him up with a with a with a missile from
a drone and then said, "Ah, sorry, our
bad." Who added that Mr. Hakani was
attending a wedding at the time of the
attack and that over 40 members of his
family were also killed. And then you
end up killing civilians virtually every
single
time, which is another problem. The
National Security Council,
um the Department of Defense and
indirectly the CIA say that they do
everything possible to avoid civilian
casualties. That's just simply not true.
First, uh, the entire intelligence
community is unrepentant when it comes
to civilian casualties. They see it as,
you know, part of the price of the
so-called war on
terror. Uh, that is uh it's a violation
of international law, of course, and
it's also inhumane. There's a very
courageous drone whistleblower by the
name of uh Daniel Hail. He was operating
a drone remotely and he fired and he
killed a 9-year-old girl and a
12-year-old girl and that's when he said
he couldn't be a part of this
[Applause]
anymore. Anybody who's involved in
counterterrorism or who has served in
the Middle East or uh South Asia for,
you know, more than one tour has been
involved in something like that. Um I've
been evacuated many times. Yeah, I'd
call this an eight.
Um, with these Hollywood problems that
we mentioned, um, the actual day-to-day
in Homeland was pretty pretty right
on. Oh my god. Yeah, I remember that
like it was yesterday. What we're seeing
in this clip is just one one aspect of
what was a very
well-coordinated long-term attack in
Mumbai. More than 100 people were
killed. I was working for ABC News when
that took place. Uh I was I was a
counterterrorism consultant at ABC News
and I decided to flip through the
channels to see what everybody was
saying about this attack. I go to CNN,
it's al-Qaeda. go to Fox, it's al-Qaeda.
MSNBC, it's al-Qaeda. And I said to my
wife, al-Qaeda has no beef with the
Indians. Why would they do something
like this? So, I went to ABC and I I get
miked up and go on and they asked me my
initial impressions and I said, I don't
think this is al-Qaeda. I think this is
a Kashmir separatist group. It turned
out it was a Kashmir separatist group.
We learned later, like a year later,
that they had carried out these attacks
with training from al-Qaeda. The
Indians, frankly, were caught
flatfooted. Certainly, they have
experience with with terrorism in
Kashmir, and this is a an issue, an
ongoing violent issue between the
Indians and the Pakistanis in the north
of the country. But in
Mumbai, they had never experienced
anything like this before. I want you
please go this way.
Yeah, the hotel staff uh this is really
the story here. They were absolutely
heroic in their uh quick thinking to
save probably hundreds of hotel guests.
They were able to to get them out of the
hotel. Yeah, this movie was right on. I
I'd give it a nine or a 10. This was an
excellent movie.
We've recently discovered a large Alleim
safe house and training cell here in
Aman. I would need your help with
surveillance, sir. So, this this was
entirely true to life. So, intelligence
um liaison cooperation happens every day
in every capital in every country around
the world.
Um it benefits everybody to have a
liazison relationship even with a
country that you might be enemies with.
That's what we saw here in this clip.
Leonardo DiCaprio went to the Jordanian
uh intelligence uh service and said uh
we need a uh we need a source inside
al-Qaeda. Gave uh his Jordanian
counterpart uh the file.
Counterterrorism is an easy one, right?
Just about everybody's going to
cooperate on counterterrorism. Well,
first of all, the Jordanian Intelligence
Service is one of the best intelligence
services in the world. They are very
sophisticated and they
are very good friends to us, great
partners. I've known him since he was a
teenager. Now he's alqaeda.
A white guy with blonde hair and blue
eyes is not going to infiltrate
al-Qaeda. But that guy will. And then
another myth that comes out of Hollywood
is that the CIA is able to directly
infiltrate foreign terrorist groups.
That's just simply not true. Half of the
people at the CIA who speak Arabic have
blonde hair and blue eyes, are
African-American, speak Arabic with uh
an an American accent. You're not going
to infiltrate a terrorist group that
way. What you have to do is to recruit
access agents who can do it on your
behalf. All we need is to establish that
he is there. Mhm. Hopefully a buzz of
messages will then pass among jihadist
networks. You have a go.
Can you imagine writing a cable to
headquarters and saying, "I have an idea
for an operation. Let's blow up the
American embassy." It's like, "No, no,
you can implement a false flag
operation." A false flag operation is
when you do
something and either blame it on someone
else or allow someone else to take
credit for it. But no, not not like we
saw in the clip. The account of the
relationship is is so good. I I'd give
it an eight. The only reason I wouldn't
give it a nine or 10 is because that the
bombing of this American facility is
just so nuts that Sorry. But yeah, the
rest of it right
on me.
That was such a great movie. So Munich
tells the story, the true story of the
attack against the Israeli Olympic team
in Munich in the 1972 Olympics. This was
an attack carried out by a Palestinian
terrorist group called uh Black
September. And um they they killed every
single Israeli athlete. Every single
one. Where's the explosion? It should
have exploded by now.
So, what we saw in that clip was was the
Israeli team killing one of the
terrorists responsible for the 1972 uh
Olympic massacre. Um, and the
Palestinians
escaped. Well, the Israeli government
set out to hunt them down one by one all
over the world and killed every single
one of them but one. There was one who,
you know, died of old age, but uh but
they got every single one of the others.
It was not one Israeli team that, you
know, went all around the world. It was
multiple Israeli teams over the course
of years. On realism, yeah, I'd give it
a seven because the the the core the
structure of the film was completely
based in fact. They sexied it up a
little bit. It was essentially
[Music]
real. Yes.
So this is based on a hijacking that
took place in the 1990s
uh of an Indian airflight 814 uh and it
was it was taken to Kandahar in
Afghanistan. Now that's important
because Kandahar is the birthplace of
the Taliban. It was the stronghold of
the Taliban. So to land in Kandahar the
hijackers really believed that they
would get everything that they wanted
because they were mujahedin, right? They
were freedom fighters, strugglers, and
uh and they they didn't get everything
they wanted. You saw in the beginning of
the clip, they wanted $200 million in
cash. They wanted dozens of of people
released. They ended up getting three
released, one of whom was rearrested.
This is an unusual clip because we don't
really see um members of the Taliban,
let alone senior of the
Taliban actually in action or at work.
As awful as the Taliban were as an
organization, in in an odd, perverted
way, they took this idea
of Muslim hospitality seriously, you've
got a plane load of hostages who've been
hijacked and flown from India to
Afghanistan,
and you can't execute them because
they're now the guests of the Taliban.
And one of the things that I think most
Americans don't understand, and I was
just as guilty of it in the immediate
aftermath of 9/11 is that the Taliban
didn't, you know, come down from the sky
and just impose themselves. These are
the the fathers, the brothers, the sons
of Afghan families. On the other side,
the Taliban couldn't understand why we
were so angry with them in 2001. They
hadn't attacked the United States.
real disconnect. This was all true. I
remember when this played out. I was
living in the Middle East. U this is a
10. I think the most convincing CIA
related film that I've seen is The
Recruit. Um the first half was
100% accurate to the point where we all
stayed to watch the credits to see who
their adviser was. not apppropo, but
what we were talking about a second ago,
the show 24 was wildly popular and Kefir
Sutherland did a fantastic job, but none
of that was believable. There was one
scene I'll never forget where he's on
the metro in Washington and he jumps out
of the metro into the Arlington Cemetery
station and he's got his gun out and
he's going like this. And I thought, "Oh
my god, are you kidding me?
You've just committed like three
felonies. Thanks for watching and if you
like this, why not click on the next
video?